<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Expedient, or, A sure &amp; easy way of reducing all dissenters whatsoever to an exact &amp; sincere obedience both to our ecclesiastical &amp; civil government</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39065</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3874</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5413</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12796349</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12796349</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93980</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39065)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93980)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 379:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Expedient, or, A sure &amp; easy way of reducing all dissenters whatsoever to an exact &amp; sincere obedience both to our ecclesiastical &amp; civil government</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:93980:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN EXPEDIENT OR A ſure &amp; eaſy way of <hi>Reducing</hi> all <hi>Diſſenters</hi> whatſoever to an exact &amp; ſincere <hi>Obedience</hi> both to our <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> &amp; <hi>Civil Government.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong all the great nations that have been, no man I believe can ſhow me the example of <hi>England,</hi> which being not only ſtill intire under the Rule of its lawful Governour, but alſo a great deal ſtronger in it ſelf, by the happy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of <hi>Scotland</hi> (its former dangerous enemy] ſhould nevertheleſs ſince the <hi>Reformation</hi> be <hi>de facto</hi> much weaker, and conſequently leſs conſiderable to our <hi>Neighbours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All <hi>Engliſh men,</hi> of what perſuaſion or intereſt ſoever, unanimouſly conclude that our differences in <hi>Religion</hi> are the cauſe; &amp; therefore as ſome of every <hi>Opinion</hi> have propoſed their <hi>Expedients</hi> for the cure of this miſfortune, ſo I hope I may take the ſame Liberty, &amp; throw in my mite alſo, being induc'd thereunto by the affection I bear my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, which I ſuppoſe moved the reſt, that have already written: and though I am born a <hi>Member</hi> of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> whoſe <hi>Liturgy</hi> &amp; <hi>Rites</hi> are ſo worthy of admiration, yet I ſhall do what I can (as far as 'tis lawful) to bridle in my <hi>Zeal,</hi> leaſt ſeeming too partial, I ſhould rather harden than mollifie our <hi>diſſenting Brethren;</hi> who happen (which is the miſery of it) to be too numerous &amp; conſiderable in this poor diſtracted <hi>Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We all know that the whole Kingdom as to <hi>Divine Worſhip</hi> is divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded (beſides its ſubdiviſions) into theſe four great Parties, <hi>viz. Church of England men, Presbyterians, Independants</hi> &amp; <hi>Papiſts;</hi> the three laſt of which we call <hi>Nonconformiſts,</hi> as contrary to the preſent Religion eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Church of England</hi> is more numerous than any, &amp; has perſons in it of all ranks &amp; conditions; but it ſeems not ſo full of <hi>Zeal</hi> as the others, becauſe it abounds with men that are too much in love with hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Intereſt, or have no Religion at all; for theſe ever flock to that <hi>Church</hi> which is in power; whether true or falſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Presbyterians</hi> have generally on their ſide the <hi>Corporations,</hi> &amp; all formal men, which they are pleas'd to call the <hi>ſober part of the Nation.</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:93980:2"/>
but as they are rich, ſo they lye more open to be haraſs'd, whenſoever the black day of tribulation happen's.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Independants</hi> of <hi>Phanatiques</hi> conſiſt only in <hi>Artizans,</hi> &amp; the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of the Land, &amp; yet are in two things very conſiderable; as firſt, let the <hi>Government</hi> do what it will with them they cannot be much poorer, ſo that in three months they will recover, &amp; be as they were; In the next place, Their <hi>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> &amp; <hi>trades</hi> are of great concernment to us.</p>
            <p>Of <hi>Papiſts</hi> there are ſeven parts of ten Gentlemen; &amp; people of great quality, &amp; therefore they fancy that their Religion is probably the trueſt, becauſe it has been profeſs'd here all along by ſo many men of parts &amp; faſhion; &amp; boaſt that it is only through Ignorance, or want of attention that the whole Nation is not as blind as themſelves. As for <hi>Perſecution</hi> they are not much terrified at it, having (as they believe) manfully endur'd it ſo many years; beſides by long practice they know not only all the wayes imaginable to evade the penalties of the <hi>Lawes,</hi> but alſo by their birth have Relations in all offices, &amp; employments, that alwayes did, &amp; ſtill do help them when they are in danger to be whipt by us.</p>
            <p>This then in three words being the <hi>intereſt</hi> and <hi>ſtate</hi> of each party, we may the eaſier find out a <hi>Remedy</hi> for our <hi>diſorders,</hi> which have ruin'd, or at beſt ſtrangely ſhatter'd one of the moſt flouriſhing <hi>Kingdomes</hi> in the world.</p>
            <p>Ever ſince the <hi>happy Reſtauration of his Majeſty,</hi> there has been ſtill a great cry in all quarters for <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> to which I have been greatly inclind, not only out of compaſſion to well meaning deluded ſouls, but out of conviction alſo that it would totally root out all <hi>Sects,</hi> &amp; erronious <hi>Opinions</hi> from among us: &amp; ſeeing we have found by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience that <hi>ſeverity</hi> has neither deſtroy'd <hi>Popery,</hi> which is ſo ridiculous to every body but its Profeſſours: nor yet prevented a troubleſome broo'd of our own, I ſay conſidering this, we ought to try what <hi>mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> will effect, ſince all wiſe men alter thoſe projects which they find deficient: at leaſt we may make tryal of it for a while, as our matchleſſe <hi>Parliaments</hi> do, that enact often Laws to continue but for ſo long, to be the better able to ſee whether they may reap the propoſed advantage by them; Nor can this tryal be any wayes prejudicial to us, if it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger neither the ſouls of men, nor cauſe a diſturbance in the <hi>Civil Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>'Tis impoſſible,</hi> (according to the profeſſion of all our moſt learned <hi>Proteſtants) to hazard our Salvation by Opinions whilſt we agree in that maine Fundamental,</hi> to wit, <hi>The ſatiſfaction of our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> for
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:93980:2"/>
otherwiſe we muſt ſhipwrack our ſelves, whether we will or no, on the unavoidable rocks of <hi>Popery;</hi> becauſe if there ſhould yet be any thing more, which we are neceſſarily to believe, an <hi>infallible interpreter,</hi> and <hi>Magiſterial Iudge</hi> to guide the ignorant &amp; unlearned would conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly follow; <hi>Magiſterial</hi> I ſay, becauſe a poor ſimple man muſt implicitely believe, as not being ever able to comprehend or underſtand ſome truths; &amp; <hi>infallible,</hi> leaſt men might be ſtill doubting whether yet they are in the right or no.</p>
            <p>No marvel then that <hi>Mr. Chillingworth</hi> (the miracle of his age) ſticks cloſe to this, thinking it very ſtrange a man ſhould be damn'd for noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which he cannot comprehend; &amp; therefore lays down <hi>Repentance from dead work<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and a belief in the coming &amp; merits of Chriſt,</hi> as the only <hi>Fundamental</hi> amongſt <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> &amp; as a thing adequate to every ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry capacity. The <hi>Papiſts</hi> who would fain come near our truths, are alſo nibbling here though they handle it another way; for they will have it too, <hi>That all men are damn'd through their own wilfulneſs in reſiſting evident things,</hi> &amp; ſay, <hi>Though Chriſt as a Prophet ſent from God may be eaſily concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by humane Reaſon, yet an infallible Church to govern his flock is eaſier comprehended and eaſier demonſtrated to a Chriſtian, than his being ſent can be proved to an I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fidel,</hi> &amp; ſo forſooth this <hi>infallible Church</hi> by its <hi>definitions,</hi> and <hi>explications</hi> makes the hardeſt <hi>myſteries</hi> as eaſie as the plaineſt.</p>
            <p>I here ſet down this pretty <hi>Doctrine</hi> dreſſ'd after the <hi>Roman faſhion,</hi> to ſhow, that if a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> ſhould not ground damnation on our wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs in rejecting things within the reach of our capacity, the very <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelves will riſe up in judgement againſt him at the laſt day, to his utter confuſion and ſhame.</p>
            <p>This <hi>moderation</hi> the eminent <hi>Doctor Taylor</hi> himſelf highly eſteem'd, &amp; this he ſo ſtoutly maintain'd in his book of <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Prophecying,</hi> that to this day it remains unanſwer'd. Many enemies I know he created to himſelf by his reconciling <hi>zeal,</hi> &amp; though by their cry he paſſes at preſent for a better <hi>practical</hi> than <hi>controverſial Divine,</hi> yet he has (as all men acknowledge made it evidently appear inconſiſtent with <hi>Proteſtant charity</hi> to damn any of our poor <hi>Diſſenters</hi> for their <hi>tenets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For firſt, can any godly <hi>Proteſtant</hi> thinke a <hi>Presbiterian</hi> a limme of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan for refuſing to conform to <hi>habits</hi> &amp; <hi>ceremonies,</hi> which every body confeſſes were neither comanded by Chriſt, nor his Apoſtles: or ſhall he be reprobated for railing againſt ſtage playes though the drift of the beſt of them is to abuſe the <hi>Brethren?</hi> Nor can the diſowning of <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> be damnable, unleſs we ſubmit our ſelves to <hi>Tradition,</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtical authority,</hi> for the <hi>Scripture</hi> has many ſeeming arguments for
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93980:3"/>
that opinion. <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> &amp; the manner of Chriſts deſcent into Hell are points diſputable among all <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> &amp; <hi>God</hi> forbid we ſhould think that every error in judgement will deprive us of all happineſſe hereafter.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Independants</hi> or <hi>Phanatiques,</hi> owe their being to the foregoing <hi>Sect,</hi> &amp; if they wildly fancy a barn as good as a Church, or a Graduate, not ſo learned as a Cobler; with other odd extravigancies (the half of which no one man can recount) let us not be more rigorous than the <hi>Pope,</hi> who only lookt upon them that came to <hi>Rome</hi> to convert him as mad; &amp; I think neither S. <hi>Peter,</hi> nor his pretended Succeſſors have lockt Bedlams out of Heaven.</p>
            <p>Nor ſhall I damn <hi>Papiſts</hi> for matters of Faith, whilſt they believe the <hi>Trinity,</hi> &amp; can patch up their other <hi>Doctrines,</hi> ſo as not really to intend thereby the diſhonour of our great <hi>Lord</hi> &amp; <hi>Maſter.</hi> For (as I ſaid before) <hi>God</hi> forbid every errour in judgment ſhould be a ſin to death.</p>
            <p>They fancy many promiſes in <hi>Scripture, That the Church ſhall never erre. That it is to be viſible in proſperity &amp; adverſity as a Iudge in all diſputes that ariſe,</hi> &amp; laugh at <hi>Proteſtants</hi> for affirming that the <hi>Scriptures</hi> are eaſie ſeeing all <hi>Sects</hi> among us quote Scripture for what they hold, &amp; yet one is often quite oppoſite to the tenets of the other in things of the higheſt nature.</p>
            <p>They preach up <hi>merits</hi> (they ſay) to encourage men to work; but tell us expreſly (when we urge to them the foulneſs of the <hi>tenet) That neither their own actions, nor the actions of any Saint can be in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſufficient to bring them to heaven, did not God promiſe to accept them as meritorious,</hi> and <hi>ſufficient by the ſuperaboundant merits of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>They honour Saints</hi> (they ſay) <hi>only becauſe they were faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of Chriſt,</hi> and believe, <hi>That theſe holy Spirits, muſt needs know our wants by their rejoycing in heaven at our converſion,</hi> &amp; <hi>That their prayers for us are much more powerful with God,</hi> than <hi>thoſe of our friends here below,</hi> which we all often implore: yet they oblige none (as they pretend) to pray to <hi>Saints</hi> except they will.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>They think becauſe ſome ſins (viz.</hi> thoſe againſt the <hi>Holy Ghoſt) ſhall not be forgiven in this world nor in the world to come, that other ſins may ſome times be forgiven in the world to come.</hi> And therefore <hi>pray for the dead (that have built upon hay ſtubble &amp; other imperfect things)</hi> whom S. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> declares (they ſay) ſhall be ſaved <hi>ſo as by fire.</hi> &amp; they more firmly alſo believe this <hi>Purgatory</hi> becauſe, the <hi>Maccabees (that fought for the maintenance of God's law) pray'd for their ſlain Brethren;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93980:3"/>
which</hi> they often urge is recorded by an unquenchable <hi>Hiſtorian,</hi> if not by a <hi>Divine Writer:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to their <hi>Idolatry</hi> in the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> they ſay, <hi>That by believing Chriſt really there 't is him they worſhip, &amp; not a piece of bread. That the thing is no leſſe poſſible according to humane reaſon than the Trinity: That the words,</hi> THIS IS MY BODY are as plain, as THERE ARE THREE THAT BEAR RECORD IN HEAVEN; &amp; <hi>That</hi> it is much for their advantage, that all ſects of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in the world grant the <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> except a few <hi>Calviniſts</hi> as they call them.</p>
            <p>By that text of <hi>Scripture, Confeſse your ſins one to another.</hi> They think their <hi>Confeſſion</hi> enjoyn'd; and that <hi>Chriſts</hi> commiſſion to his Diſciples <hi>to bind &amp; to looſe</hi> authorizes their Prieſts <hi>Abſolutions</hi> and <hi>Interdictions.</hi> And before many of their books of <hi>Pilgrimages, Reliques, Pictures,</hi> &amp; the like (to ſhow their worſhip is relative) they print this piece of <hi>Saint Jerom's</hi> Epiſtle againſt <hi>Vigilantius.</hi> 
               <q>We honour the Reliques of Martyrs, to render adoration to him for the love of whom they were Martyrs, we honour the ſervants, that what we do for their ſervice may be refer'd to their Master, who ſays, He that receives you receives me.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhould never have done, were I to ſet down all their <hi>opinions,</hi> &amp; <hi>Jeſuiticall</hi> gloſſes, but this I may ſay for them, that they have much leſſe to anſwer, ſince they really think themſelves in the right, &amp; are ſo united in their <hi>Fundamentalls,</hi> whilſt the poor <hi>Proteſtants</hi> (to the great ſhame &amp; weakening of the <hi>common cauſe</hi>) quarrell irreconcileably about nicetyes, &amp; then divide &amp; ſubdivide without end.</p>
            <p>Far be it therefore from us to damne theſe <hi>Papiſts</hi> though <hi>ignorant,</hi> eſpecially ſeeing, we muſt do the like then to the <hi>Lutherns,</hi> who are not only <hi>Proteſtants</hi> but the firſt <hi>Reformers</hi> alſo: for their Churches are cram'd with <hi>Crucifixes,</hi> &amp; <hi>Pictures;</hi> and which is more, they as really be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> as the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelf; the <hi>main point</hi> in which he &amp; his brood commit <hi>Idolatry,</hi> as the <hi>Church of England</hi> and the other beſt <hi>reform'd Churches</hi> hold.</p>
            <p>Let not therefore our paſſion ſhut up heaven againſt any to whom our <hi>Savour</hi> has open'd it; &amp; ſince <hi>Proteſtants</hi> themſelves do ſo diſagree (as ſometimes each man in a family is of a different Church) let us be the more charitable in our cenſures, according to the healing advice of many a painful <hi>Divine;</hi> and thus may the <hi>Papiſts</hi> be baffled with their own di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, <hi>viz; That they differ in ſchool points only, &amp; not in fundamentalls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here I deſire not to be miſunderſtood, for I hold many other Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines extremely advantageous to poor ſouls, and heartily wiſh all men of my opinion, but nothing but time and new methods can unite us without the utter ruine of the <hi>Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:93980:4"/>
            <p>Having thus like a good <hi>Proteſtant</hi> prov'd, That <hi>Indulgence</hi> to <hi>diſſenters</hi> though (they ſhould encreaſe by it, as ſome vainly fancy) cannot hinder their <hi>ſalvation,</hi> becauſe all that do well may be ſaved; I will now come to the <hi>civil Government,</hi> &amp; ſhow you that it will be ſo far from cauſing <hi>diſturbances,</hi> or endangering the <hi>true Religion</hi> that in ten years there ſhall not be a <hi>diſſenter</hi> left to piſs againſt the wall; &amp; this I hope (if practicable) muſt ſatisfy even thoſe, that limite <hi>God's mercy,</hi> eſpecially ſince they know how firmly ſects are already rooted here, &amp; could never be extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pated by the ſeverity of our <hi>Laws.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have often laugh'd to hear perſons of each <hi>Sect</hi> among us pretend that their Religion teaches nothing but <hi>obedience</hi> to Magiſtrates, whilſt all others foment <hi>Rebellion.</hi> Now for my part I would abſolutely truſt no Religion in the world with the full power of depoſing Princes, no more than I would have an <hi>Infidel</hi> truſt his wife in bed with me becauſe I am a <hi>Chriſtian.</hi> 'Tis moſt certain that the true religion of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> comands as well and exact <hi>obedience</hi> to our <hi>Rulers,</hi> as that we ſhould not <hi>commit adultery;</hi> but yet whilſt men are men, many of the Profeſſors of this truth (what by the force of a partial appetite, &amp; ſelf <hi>interreſte'd</hi> diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions) when they have oppertunity, often tranſgreſs thoſe two pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, though as poſitively command as can be: &amp; therefore ſome doubt whether all the <hi>Primitive Christians</hi> would have been ſo patient under <hi>Nero, Domitian, Diocletian, &amp;c.</hi> had they had power enough to contend: Nor will I more paſſe my word that the <hi>Grand Segnior</hi> ſhould continue <hi>Emperour</hi> &amp; <hi>Mahometan,</hi> were the ſword wholly in the hands of his <hi>Chriſtian</hi> ſubjects, than that all the members of the <hi>Church of England</hi> would have ſubmitted to our preſent <hi>Monarch,</hi> had he yeilded to the <hi>Papists,</hi> who were as buiſy (they ſay) as Bees to convert him.</p>
            <p>All men whatſoever affect to have their Ptince of their Religion, becauſe they fancy it moſt for the glory of <hi>God,</hi> but nothing heightens this <hi>zeal</hi> ſo much as <hi>perſecution;</hi> for whenſoever there is difficulty of obtaining our will, the deſire of enjoyment encreaſes; as we ſee even in women that often riſque life, fortune, honour, &amp; all to enjoy a <hi>Gallant,</hi> when as if they afterwards marry (&amp; then there will be no need of comming in by the window) 'tis a thouſand to one but they preſently loath each others converſation, &amp; bed. Beſides this natural proneneſſe to purſue what is hindred us (for <hi>paſſions</hi> often bear ſway even in our ſpiritual actions) ſelf preſervation alſo or the hopes to be quiet puts the brains of <hi>diſſenters</hi> upon propagating their Religion; nor is it a ſmall argument to many of the truth of a new <hi>Doctrine,</hi> to ſee men ſuffer for it.</p>
            <p>This we have experimentally ſeen here at home in every party that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93980:4"/>
now contends with the <hi>Church;</hi> for what could be more irreſiſtable than <hi>Presbytery</hi> in the beginning of the late war; &amp; how many men, women, &amp; children, would have willingly ventur'd their lives for the <hi>Cauſe</hi> whilſt kept under? &amp; yet within three years or thereabouts after it's eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, 'twas kick'd down even by thoſe who had before ſet it up with ſuch <hi>zeal</hi> &amp; <hi>hazard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Phanaticiſme</hi> (as well mankind inlightned with the laſt ſpark of reaſon will acknowledge) has no greater enemy than it ſelf, nor ever did, nor ever can ſtand, becauſe it wants all <hi>principles</hi> of <hi>ſettlement;</hi> &amp; therefore 'tis we that blow the party into ſome appearance of <hi>unity,</hi> in hoping by diſturbance to haſten their ruine.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Popery,</hi> let us conſider it in <hi>Queen Elizabeths</hi> time, &amp; we ſhall find in our <hi>Proteſtant Hiſtorians</hi> that for the firſt ten years of her reign no man as a <hi>Papiſt</hi> ſuffered either in his life, or Eſtate, &amp; yet from a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful the <hi>Reform'd</hi> became much more than half the <hi>Kingdom:</hi> but after that the Government began to enact <hi>ſanguinary</hi> &amp; penal Laws we find that <hi>Allen, Philopater,</hi> &amp; the reſt of their active Writers inſiſted upon no argument more (to prove the truth of their Religion) than that <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of all ſorts became daily <hi>Papiſts,</hi> but not one in 7. years left them, except ſome ſcandalous fellow which was a greater advantage than loſſe to them.</p>
            <p>Let us look in the next place on their <hi>Jeſuiticall Seminaries</hi> at <hi>Douay</hi> &amp; <hi>Saint Omers,</hi> &amp; you ſhall find them (as knowing men have aſſur'd me) much emptier now they can carry <hi>popiſh</hi> Children over with little danger, than in the former dayes, when it was done by great bribes, &amp; they often indited for fugitives alſo.</p>
            <p>Again if we reflect upon our <hi>late Rebellion,</hi> it was called by many (as I well remember) the <hi>popes harveſt,</hi> &amp; <hi>Halcyon dayes;</hi> &amp; yet we know they loſt beſides others of note, two <hi>Marqueſſes</hi> at a clap (I mean the heirs apparent of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> &amp; <hi>Worceſter</hi>) the like of which cannot be paralleld in the greateſt ſeverities of the <hi>Queen,</hi> nor in the violent ſtorme that univerſally fell after the <hi>Powder Treaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, concerning <hi>Proclamations</hi> &amp; the like, what man ever found the leaſt good by them? If there be any thing got, the Prieſts are the gainers: for (every body ſay's) not one ſtir's out of <hi>England,</hi> &amp; 'tis likely alſo by being in a ſeeming kind of danger, that they are the more careſs'd by their <hi>Penitents.</hi> Nay if all things were well examin'd, we ſhall find that the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> themſelves do ever pitty them in diſtreſs, &amp; that there are never more <hi>converſions</hi> than in the height of theſe pudders, which 'tis no
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93980:5"/>
wonder if they enter into their <hi>Anualls</hi> as <hi>Perſecutions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If <hi>puniſhment</hi> then ſerves only to encreaſe the number of <hi>Sectaries,</hi> why ſhould we be ſo much their friends, and do them courteſies to be rayl'd at for our pains? <hi>Courteſies</hi> I ſay, becauſe their <hi>Domine</hi> or <hi>Godly Paſtor</hi> would otherwiſe ſtarve, whereas now there's nothing thought too good for him; and the flock then would have alſo leiſure to conſider their extravigance, which now the <hi>pleaſure</hi> of being <hi>haraſs'd</hi> hinders. No <hi>Cavaliers</hi> will wonder at my joyning the word <hi>pleaſure</hi> to <hi>haraſſing,</hi> ſince I dare ſay there are not any of thoſe great and loyal ſubjects, though they now poſſeſſe places ſuitable to their merits, but had formerly more ſatisfaction in one poor play by ſtealth at <hi>Haynes's,</hi> in one meeting at <hi>Doctor Gunning's</hi> in danger, or in contriving any half Moon-plot over a pint of ſack, than ever they enjoyed (as to their own particular) ſince the abſolute eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of his <hi>Majeſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the nature of fraile man, and if the beſt and wiſeſt of men cool a little by enjoyment, what muſt they do that have no other guide but <hi>paſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I wiſh then that our <hi>Sectaries</hi> had <hi>churches</hi> allowed them, &amp; all the <hi>priviledges of their brith right</hi> as they call it; nor am I yet their Advocate, but the Nation's, as hoping to preſerve it's Inhabitants &amp; deſtroy their fooliſh blind <hi>Zeal,</hi> which has been ſo fatal to us.</p>
            <p>Their <hi>Churches</hi> or <hi>Congregations</hi> I would have under penalty pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique &amp; regiſter'd, which hath nothing of particularity in it, ſeeing all the <hi>Churches</hi> in the Kingdom are ſo. By this means his <hi>Majeſty</hi> would know their <hi>perſons, manners,</hi> &amp; <hi>Doctrine,</hi> which now by their meeting in holes, he is wholly unacquainted with; &amp; if any man then ſpake in the leaſt againſt the Government, he ſhould be made an Example with all the ſeverity that could be thought of.</p>
            <p>I have heard ſay that in <hi>Holland</hi> (where no Religion is unwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come if any Miniſter in his ſermon, or other ſpiritual function, meddles with <hi>state affairs,</hi> the Magiſtrates ſend him next day a pair of ſhoos to carry him forthwith out of the Province; &amp; preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he provides for his march, otherwiſe he is ſure to be hang'd unlamented; nor do they ever touch more than the <hi>offender,</hi> which proceed's not ſo much from <hi>juſtice</hi> or <hi>Compaſſion,</hi> as <hi>Prudence;</hi> it being certain no penalty can ſo ſurely tye up an Incendiary's tongue as (when he ſuffers) not to be pittied by his Party.</p>
            <p>For to puniſh the whole <hi>Body</hi> (as the Engliſh cuſtome is) for the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93980:5"/>
faults of ſome <hi>members,</hi> makes them all deſperate, racking many times their brain to defend an action (the then <hi>common cauſe</hi> which otherwiſe they would have diſown'd, without difficulty; and beſides it is a kind of real martyrdom when a man actually ſuffers either in his life or eſtate, for a crime which perchance ſtrictly and truly he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>minates.</p>
            <p>No wonder then, that our <hi>Papiſts</hi> not only reckon themſelves <hi>Martyrs,</hi> but are cryd up &amp; eſteemd for ſuch by ſo many Forrain Princes; which muſt needs draw a ſcandal upon the <hi>Nation,</hi> &amp; ſo do the <hi>Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> a prejudice both at home and abroad, if theſe encreaſe, and gain re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e alſo by their ſufferings. I cannot therefore but be highly diſſatiſfied with our <hi>common Juſtice,</hi> which entails Rebellion on a <hi>Sect,</hi> and inſulting too much over the we kneſs of mankind, neceſſarily (as it were) inclines from Father to ſon unprincipled men to all villany and treaſon.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore call to mind the <hi>Scotch Presbyterian Rebellion</hi> in 66 laſt, and ſee what a ruine it would have been to <hi>England,</hi> had his <hi>Majeſty</hi> inſtead of his own great <hi>predence</hi> and merciful temper followed their councel who thought it fit to purſue our <hi>preſbyterians</hi> at home, as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plotters with thoſe actually in arms, This would have driven all into the utmoſt deſpair, eſpecially thoſe that loved the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Kingdom</hi> beſt; for then they would have deem'd it impoſſible to ſatiſfie, <hi>&amp;</hi> conſequently thought ill deſigns the beſt of their play, nor would they have lookt upon themſelves or children otherwiſe than ſlaves, ſince no ſlavery is equal to that, of being always ſuſpected by the Government. Many that are now faithful, would then have been not only incenſed, but perchance have turnd their <hi>bibles</hi> over and over to find again arguments to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Rebellion; for what will not men fancy <hi>God</hi> ſayes when tis abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary for their ends.</p>
            <p>Were every man that now heartily rejoyces at a Thiefs execution at <hi>Tyburn,</hi> to ſuffer with the malefactor, we ſhould not only ſee <hi>theft</hi> defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by its preſent condemners, but reckond for a <hi>virtue</hi> alſo. Some would cry up the life of man for an ineſtimable jewel, and to be preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all world<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y traſh Others would term <hi>propriety, a tyrannick, &amp; unjuſt u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpation,</hi> with the like metaphyſical fancies, nay the tricks of a Raſcal would be then called the effect of a dextrous wit, &amp; the ſetting upon two or three unarmed G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſiers, the height of all valour and courage.</p>
            <p>Theres nothing can ever deſtroy us in <hi>England</hi> but diſagreement, nor ſhall the Government ever fail of being thought the common enemy by all <hi>Nonconformiſts,</hi> whilſt the folly or Knavery of ſome few is imputed to the whole gang in general.</p>
            <p>If this way of proceeding were lay'd aſide (which now ſtrongly ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments them) their <hi>Congregations</hi> would quickly be well ſatiſfied with
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93980:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the condemnation of a guilty <hi>Member,</hi> as we ordinarily are at what paſſes at the <hi>old Bayly,</hi> or at any of our other <hi>Seſſions.</hi> It may be ſome might ſtrive to mince the matter of fact (as daily friends do in all faults committed) but none would then defend a crime to be no crime, which is the thing I ſolely inſiſt upon, for from thence ariſe all our diſputes &amp; factions.</p>
            <p>'Tis an <hi>error</hi> to think there can be a great <hi>Body</hi> of men inconſiſtent with Government, ſince to be lawleſs is as oppoſite to the nature of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind in general, as death it ſelf. Every ſober man therefore (let his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion be what it will) find's out ſome diſtinction or other to prevent confuſion, &amp; to conform to Laws that tend to Government. The <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians</hi> are too diſcreet &amp; rich to be <hi>anarchica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> &amp; whoſoever has, &amp; loves riches, will be always fond of Laws that preſerve his right to them The <hi>Phanatiques</hi> are generally harmleſs &amp; well meaning; &amp; though a <hi>Quaker</hi> will not ſet out his Tithes, he will bid the <hi>Miniſter</hi> or <hi>Tithing man</hi> take them: nay if he find loſs by their carving, he will at length do it himſelf with this or the like ſalvo, that <hi>'Tis the old man &amp; not the new that payes the Hireling that Judaical abomination:</hi> nor do theſe poor peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple refuſe (it ſeems) to engage to live peaceably, as their friend Mr. <hi>Pen</hi> tells us in his <hi>Great Caſe.</hi> Now for the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> the greateſt &amp; moſt abſolute Princes of the World are not only of their profeſſion, but our own King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom alſo was extremely conſiderable under their <hi>Goverment,</hi> &amp; our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Laws and prudent old cuſtomes were of their framing; as they well know, &amp; alſo vaunt in their late <hi>Apology</hi> &amp; <hi>Reply.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides though the <hi>Papiſts</hi> of <hi>England</hi> are ſtill ſo great Aſſertors of the <hi>Popes</hi> power in <hi>Spirituals,</hi> that I really believe by what I have read &amp; ſeen that there would more die for him here, then in any two Countreys in the world, yet we know that in the very depth of <hi>Popery</hi> no body ſtruck more bold &amp; home at all temporal encroachments of the <hi>Romiſh See,</hi> than the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> for they not only made ſtrict prohibitions againſt the <hi>coming</hi> in of <hi>Legates</hi> without leave againſt <hi>publication of bulls,</hi> and the like; but alſo enacted thoſe nipping Laws of <hi>Mortmain,</hi> ſo that no body could voluntarily &amp; of his own head give one foot of Land to the <hi>Church,</hi> Nor at this day do I find, (for truly I have made particular enquiry about it) any French man more willing than our preſent <hi>Papiſts</hi> to tye up the <hi>Popes</hi> hands from medling with the <hi>civil Government</hi> of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>If therefor all or any of theſe <hi>Diſſenters</hi> be now heaving at the <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> 'tis becauſe they are diſtinguiſh'd from the reſt of the <hi>Nation,</hi> &amp; made as uncapable of many things as ſtrangers &amp; aliens; nor do's animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity or a rebellious ſpirit always proceed from the Religion men profeſs but from the frailty of nature which makes them often partial, &amp; take the dictates of their appetite for truth &amp; reaſon. Now were no <hi>Engliſh Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> (as long as obedient to the lawful <hi>power</hi>) inconvenienc'd for his <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:93980:6"/>
'tis impoſſible but <hi>Sectaries</hi> would be as heartily ſollicitous for the good of the <hi>Nation,</hi> as any man elſe whatſoever.</p>
            <p>This moſt evidently appears by the <hi>Welſh,</hi> who (whilſt we ſuſpected &amp; uſed them with rigor) were ever unquiet, &amp; our moſt deadly enemies, but after we had recieved them as friends, &amp; made them partakers of all the <hi>priviledges</hi> of the Kingdom, they not only for got <hi>our ſtrange uſage of their Princes the loſs of their Lands, &amp; the Egyptian ſlavery</hi> they were under but ſo united themſelves with us, that our loſſes are now theirs, &amp; theirs ours; nor have they ſince ever ſtirr'd or made ill uſe of our favours; but (on the contrary by them, both they and we are become <hi>one people, &amp; one nation</hi> without the leaſt rancour, or grudge; nay ſo fond have they been of our <hi>Monarchy</hi> (which once they hated <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bove all things) that four parts of five of them were faithful to his <hi>late Majeſty,</hi> whilſt ſuch a number of <hi>Engliſh</hi> were up againſt him. If then <hi>gentleneſs</hi> &amp; <hi>intereſt</hi> could reconcile long feuds, &amp; make men from mortal foes become the greateſt friends why may not we expect by the like method the like ſucceſs in theſe our preſent diſtractions?</p>
            <p>Ther's one <hi>argument</hi> (as 'tis thought) of great weight againſt this <hi>liberty of Conſcience,</hi> viz. <hi>That all diſſenters when they were in power would tolerate no Religion but their own,</hi> (as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in time paſt, &amp; the <hi>Proteſtant Sectaries</hi> in the late rebellion) &amp; therefore in <hi>Iuſtice</hi> they ought now to be ſerved in the ſame manner. The matter of <hi>fact</hi> is granted &amp; taken out of their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons I know, yet nevertheleſs if perſecuting <hi>Chriſtians</hi> for <hi>conſcience</hi> be in it ſelf againſt <hi>charity,</hi> we muſt not retaliate, &amp; render like for like. but on the other ſide, if the <hi>lawful Magiſtrate</hi> may puniſh <hi>tender conſciences</hi> when he thinks it for the honor of <hi>God,</hi> &amp; quiet of the Government, this may perchance a little touch the <hi>Preſbyterians</hi> &amp; <hi>Phanaetiques</hi> (who were our Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers by indirect means but then we can never blame any longer the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> for what they did, becauſe their Goverment (as to its Juriſdiction) was as lawful as ours, &amp; their <hi>plea</hi> conſequently unanſwerable, <hi>viz,</hi> That they really <hi>fancy'd their Religion true, &amp; the Proteſtant heretical; That they thought it would for ever diſtract &amp; diſquiet the nation to permit new Doctrine;</hi> &amp; in ſhort, <hi>That they proceeded according to Magna Charta, &amp; other Laws enacted by the legal Authority of the Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No man can therefore better defend the <hi>Marian days,</hi> &amp; all <hi>Popiſh ſeverity;</hi> than by adviſing the puniſhment of <hi>Non-conformiſts,</hi> &amp; practiſing it as we do: But if we would have the <hi>Church of Englands</hi> great beauty appear, &amp; be the <hi>true ſpouſe without ſpot or wrinkle,</hi> we muſt neceſſarily refrain from doing thoſe things, which they whom we blame are deem'd guilty of.</p>
            <p>It is pleaſant to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee now a days how <hi>Presbyterians, Independants &amp; Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,</hi> (though really no great friends) begin to claw one another; &amp; who
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93980:7"/>
can blame them for it, or would not think them otherwiſe fools, ſince they all lye under the ſame laſh?</p>
            <p>I remember when <hi>Dr. Hewet</hi> was to be executed, our <hi>Church of England</hi> &amp; <hi>City Divines</hi> joyn'd together (though they hated one another ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently) to petition <hi>Cromwel</hi> for him; at which ſome perſons of quality wondring one night at <hi>Dr. Duns, Sr. Henry Blunt</hi> anſwerd, that he thought there was nothing extraordinary in that action; for (ſaid he) I have near my houſe a <hi>Common</hi> where my pigs, &amp; my neighbours feed, &amp; there I dayly ſee that they eagerly fight &amp; bite one another at the trough, But if a dog happens to fall upon any one, the reſt will preſently take the part of the oppreſs'd with all the zeal and fury imaginable.</p>
            <p>'Tis certain both <hi>Greek &amp; Trojan</hi> will unite when they find it their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt to do it, &amp; what greater intereſt can any man have; than the good of his <hi>Country,</hi> if he be capable of participating of all the advantages that accrue. I do not therefore infer that preſently a <hi>Quaker</hi> muſt be made <hi>Maſter of the Ceremonies,</hi> or <hi>Revels,</hi> but that if he can dance, &amp; put of his hat with as good a grace as another, he ſhould not looſe the hopes of theſe places by reaſon of his Religion; for though thouſands will never emerge but be beggars and Tinkers, ſhould all our <hi>Colliers</hi> be fraught'd with Gold, yet theſe very contemptible men would think the <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> uneaſie, and perchance wiſh its ruine; were they by <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> never to riſe to any higher pith.</p>
            <p>Were we all of one <hi>opinion,</hi> no man ſhould be more willing to keep out <hi>Sects</hi> than my ſelf; for then twould be both feaſible and lawful; but ſince things are come to this height, 'tis now impoſſible to do it by <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>verity,</hi> for all violent courſes wil only exaſperate more than half our ſubj. &amp; cauſe many to catch at all ſeditious opportuni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies that ſhall at any time occur.</p>
            <p>But ſome men (like <hi>Iuſtice Over<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce</hi>) muſt be puniſhing, for otherwiſe they fancy all <hi>Diſcipline</hi> loſt; &amp; therefore of ſuch I would fain know, ſince all <hi>Diſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers</hi> cannot in <hi>Prudence</hi> be brought to the ring, which of them would they bate had they power?</p>
            <p>To fall foul o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Preſbyterians</hi> would be madneſs, for who would not deem that action ſo, which muſt needs provoke a <hi>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch,</hi> a <hi>prudent,</hi> &amp; a <hi>nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rous Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty</hi> to be eternal enemies to the Government, &amp; yet no <hi>Proteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant</hi> can call their errors in Faith, damnable. They once err'd we know, but this may be a means to make their children alſo faulty; &amp; truly I doubt not but the miſeries they at laſt ſuffer'd in the <hi>late Rebellion,</hi> for wealthy m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n muſt ſmart in ſuch diſorders) will cauſe them to be for the future <hi>faithful Engliſh men,</hi> unleſs new <hi>exaſperations</hi> pervert both their <hi>reſolution &amp; reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Twere pity alſo, methinks to be always puniſhing <hi>Phanatiques,</hi> who ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther want a good <hi>Phiſitian,</hi> &amp; <hi>Cephaliques,</hi> than the <hi>authority</hi> of a <hi>Conſtable.</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:93980:7"/>
I am ſure (as I ſaid before) it makes them more obſtinate, as fancying themſelves like the <hi>primitivs Chriſtians,</hi> whilſt the <hi>Hollanders</hi> grow rich by our loſſes, ffording them that quiet which they find not at home, &amp; thereby become maſters of thoſe <hi>manufactures</hi> which formerly we <hi>alone</hi> could brag of.</p>
            <p>Or ſhall we then vent our fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y againſt <hi>Papiſts,</hi> &amp; make our ſelves ſtill ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous to our <hi>neighbouring Princes,</hi> who receiving odd accounts from their Agents, think us a weak people &amp; eaſy to be diſtracted by vain fears &amp; jealouſies? Nor can it certainly be for the good or honour of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to perſecute thoſe, who have ſhewed ſo much <hi>loyalty,</hi> that no race of men could ever parallel them unleſs the true <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>Church of England;</hi> &amp; that which makes me yet more their friend, is that at preſent (though we have often provokt them) they keep no <hi>private caballing</hi> with either <hi>France, Spain, Pope, Devil,</hi> or any thing that is all (for had they done it we ſhould have ſmelt it out long ago) but on the contrary, they have ever the <hi>King</hi> in their mouths, as if the <hi>Rump</hi> were now on foot, and expreſs as much grief at our <hi>publiquem fortunes</hi> as any other <hi>Subj ct</hi> in the <hi>Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I defie all their <hi>Prieſts &amp; Fryers</hi> to alter my principles in Religion, yet I do acknowledge their <hi>Church</hi> to be a <hi>Church</hi> as our learned <hi>Prelates &amp; Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines</hi> have taught me; nor can I but decrie thoſe that will damn our <hi>great Grand-fathers, &amp;</hi> conſequently all before them; for I am ſure every body then were <hi>Papiſts</hi> with a vengeance, unleſſe ſometimes two or three foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh <hi>Lollards</hi> ſtarted up, who were far liker the <hi>Diſciples</hi> of <hi>Fox &amp; Naylor,</hi> than <hi>Members</hi> of the true <hi>Proteſtant Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Away then with perſecuting <hi>Chriſtians</hi> purely for <hi>Conſcience,</hi> which is the only <hi>hadveſt</hi> for <hi>Knave, &amp;</hi> of this here at home we have two moſt wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful examples; For neither had the <hi>Head</hi> of our <hi>long Rebellion</hi> been ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully aſſiſted at firſt, could their <hi>zealous abettors</hi> have been aſſured of their Religion, Nor was it ever poſſible for <hi>Cromwel</hi> to have raisd himſelf to that pitch he was in, but by laying hold on the <hi>tender Conſciences</hi> of men, who deſpairing of favour from a lawfuler <hi>Government,</hi> became at laſt <hi>bands</hi> to his <hi>ambition, &amp;</hi> then ſhar'd with him in that rich &amp; plentyful booty,</p>
            <p>Away I ſay, with this <hi>perſecution,</hi> the chief cauſe alſo of ſo muſt <hi>Atheiſme</hi> amongſtus; for men who want courage to ſuffer, by ſinning often againſt their <hi>Conſciences,</hi> become hardned in time, &amp; in ſtead of ever really appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Religion impos'd think every thing at laſt a meer cheat, &amp; ſo from harmleſs people erronius it may be at firſt in points of ſmall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment) grow fixt by degree in all <hi>infidelity &amp; prophaneneſſe;</hi> nor has any one thing been more deſtruct ve to our G vernment than ſo many <hi>Oaths,</hi> for moſt that were truly ill men never ſcrupled the taking of them when as <hi>Diſſentrs</hi> that ſtood on <hi>Principles</hi> have always refus'd them &amp; oftenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93980:8"/>
ſmartly ſuffer'd for it. Thus the <hi>best</hi> fall only within reach of the <hi>laws</hi> whilſt the moſt <hi>factious</hi> &amp; <hi>dangerous</hi> (againſt whom thoſe very <hi>laws</hi> were intended) eſcape their deſerved puniſhment.</p>
            <p>I profeſs to the whole world I have no inclination to the <hi>Religion</hi> of our <hi>Sectaries,</hi> but their <hi>perſons;</hi> who being ſo numerous can never be miſus'd without an unſpeakable inconvenience to us all, &amp; though I have been a <hi>Cavalier</hi> (I thank <hi>God</hi>) ever ſince the name came up (&amp; to this day dote upon any thing that truly was of the <hi>party</hi>) yet I have laid aſide all ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſity againſt our old enemies, becauſe I am ſure it is for the intereſt now of that <hi>Prince</hi> whoſe <hi>Rights</hi> we all heretofore ſo eagerly aſſerted.</p>
            <p>As Rebels againſt the <hi>State</hi> muſt be pardon'd whenſoever they are many, even ſo we muſt do with <hi>Diſſenters</hi> in Religion, for though the executing of three or four Traytors may be <hi>Iustice,</hi> yet to hang up many millions, would be termed <hi>cruelty</hi> let the <hi>fact</hi> be what it will.</p>
            <p>Let there be a <hi>general Toleration,</hi> for unleſs it be general we ſhall never be at reſt, but furniſh <hi>knaves</hi> ſtill (as I ſaid before) with advantages to couſin poor people, &amp; provoke them (being once deluded) to kick againſt their <hi>lawful Magiſtrate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let <hi>Presbyterians</hi> whine their fill, &amp; tell us of <hi>Soulſaving-ſending home-comforts;</hi> let <hi>Phanatiques</hi> ſigh till they be in earneſt; &amp; let <hi>Papiſts</hi> tire them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with their <hi>Pater noſters</hi> &amp; <hi>Ave Maries,</hi> &amp; then I am ſure they will all of them ſoon find the honour &amp; welfare of their <hi>Country</hi> to be their only <hi>intereſt.</hi> Nor is there danger that the bare hopes of recovering the <hi>publick Lands</hi> they once bought in the late <hi>civil War,</hi> will make the <hi>Body</hi> of <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiques</hi> fond of alterations; ſince they very well know, let what changes ſoever happen (which <hi>God</hi> in his mercy defend us always from) the <hi>new Adventures</hi> will get the prey to themſelves, for that muſt be proportioned to each Actor, according to what be <hi>then</hi> do's, &amp; not to what he or his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>formerly</hi> did: but though by rebellion they can have no aſſurance of reenjoying their old ſilly purchaſes, or any temporal gain more than other new partizans, yet all of them are ſure that <hi>Liberty f Conſcience</hi> will be granted them from the firſt, what faction ſoever takes up arms againſt the King, which muſt needs make even quiet <hi>Sectaries</hi> greedy to hear of inſurrections &amp; broile. How eaſily therefore will <hi>Toleration</hi> hinder this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural tendency, &amp; how neceſſary are the means of preventing ſuch an ill? for <hi>wo</hi> be to that country to ſo great a part of whoſe Inhabitants, <hi>ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> &amp; <hi>diſorders</hi> are a certain advantage.</p>
            <p>'Twere needleſs to mention the many places where <hi>Toleration</hi> even at preſent is granted, as well in <hi>Popiſh</hi> as <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Countryes, which ſhows all diſcourſes againſt its unpracticableneſs chimerical, &amp; the idle whimſies of men's brains; nay, we that know that in <hi>Holland,</hi> &amp; in many provinces of <hi>Germany</hi> (beſides ſeveral <hi>plantations,</hi> in the <hi>Eaſt</hi> &amp; <hi>Weſt Indies,</hi> &amp; a thouſand
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93980:8"/>
other places) <hi>Diſſenters</hi> are not only good <hi>Subjects</hi> &amp; make the <hi>publick intereſt</hi> of the <hi>Country</hi> their <hi>own,</hi> but alſo after their playing the fool a while, they become tyr'd at laſt by being let alone, &amp; then commonly conform themſelves to the Religion of the Government under which they happen then to be.</p>
            <p>Nor is this all for <hi>Toleration</hi> will convert ſeveral <hi>Sects</hi> from thoſe abominable <hi>opinion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> as to <hi>Obedience</hi> which now they are thought tainted with; becauſe whilſt they ſecretly meet in by places what may not their Paſtors infuſe into them, &amp; what will they not eaſily ſwallow; being diſcontented &amp; troubled? On the other ſide, if their <hi>Churches</hi> be <hi>publique</hi> &amp; allowed by <hi>Authority,</hi> we may all then not only truly know what is taught by them but alſo their <hi>Congregations</hi> (being enjoyned to give up in writing the <hi>ſum</hi> of their <hi>tenets</hi>) will without <hi>peradventure</hi> ſoon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to the due <hi>obedience</hi> mentioned; for 'tis certain to all mankind that things poſitively againſt the <hi>Law of Nature</hi> (as <hi>Murther, Theft, Adultery, Liberty to kill Kings</hi> when we pleaſe, &amp; the like) will never be permitted by any <hi>Power</hi> in the world, &amp; therefore the <hi>Knaves,</hi> or <hi>Ringleaders</hi> of our <hi>Sectaries</hi> (whoſe ambition &amp; deſign is to draw people after them) dare not inſiſt upon ſuch <hi>Doctrines,</hi> as know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it canot be ſo much as coniv'd at by his <hi>Majeſty;</hi> &amp; inſtead of being thought martyrs they are ſure alſo to be deſerted by their own <hi>followers,</hi> who will ſoon diſcover the cheat, when they find the <hi>King</hi> really <hi>Indulgent</hi> &amp; <hi>good natur'd</hi> &amp; ſhockt at nothing, but at that which is deſtructive &amp; hurtful in it ſelf: for as I ſaid before, There's no <hi>Body</hi> of men truly <hi>anarchicall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This will cauſe them then at leaſt to explicate the worſt, &amp; moſt ſeditious <hi>Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines</hi> ſo, that <hi>Rebellion</hi> muſt be own'd <hi>unlawful,</hi> &amp; the <hi>perſons</hi> of <hi>Kings</hi> eſteemed <hi>Sacred;</hi> by which great numbers will be undeluded, &amp; made faithful, ſeeing that publickly condemned by their own <hi>Aſſembly</hi> which now a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> beſt lyes <hi>undetermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> &amp; therefore may be aſſerted by the <hi>Preacher</hi> when he pleaſes. Moreover this enjoyning each <hi>Congregation</hi> to give in a <hi>Confeſſion</hi> of their <hi>Faith,</hi> will certainly reduce all <hi>Sectaries</hi> to their wits; for thus they will be accuſtomed to ſtand to ſome <hi>principles</hi> or other, wheras now they have nothing <hi>poſitive,</hi> &amp; conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly can hardly be confuted, the only aim of their <hi>political &amp; cunning teachers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it be then <hi>true proteſtant charity</hi> not to damn <hi>Chriſtians</hi> for <hi>opinions</hi> whilſt they agree in the <hi>main,</hi> If moreover <hi>Sects</hi> are already ſo fixt, that they cannot be rooted out by force without deſtroying the Nation, and if <hi>ſeverity</hi> blinds them that would otherwiſe ſee the truth, and makes them perſevere in their errors, entailing alſo a hatred againſt the Government on moſt of the Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity (which at preſent weakens and may for the future again undo us) where is the fruit of tormenting men for their <hi>conſciences,</hi> unleſs it be to furniſh our <hi>Sectaries</hi> (eſpecially <hi>papiſts</hi>) with an unanſwerable argument for any action committed whilſt the power was in their hands.</p>
            <p>But if <hi>liberty</hi> were granted if guilty men only ſuffer'd &amp; not their <hi>parties,</hi> &amp; if <hi>diſſenters</hi> were capable of favour &amp; truſt, all people would joyn in the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Goverment, <hi>Delinquents</hi> might be puniſh'd to the ſatiſfaction of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93980:9"/>
the reſt alſo the deſignes of all dangerous Miſcreants would be wholly fruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; &amp; in that conſiſts the only poſſibility of new troubles. Nor can <hi>Diſſenters</hi> by <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> have any pretence in the leaſt to <hi>Biſhopricks, D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anries,</hi> or our other preſent <hi>Eccleſiaſtical preferments,</hi> more than to any mans private lands; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they never contributed to them, &amp; therefore the <hi>King</hi> (had be no other title) muſt diſpoſe of them, being ever <hi>heir</hi> where there is none; &amp; to how many men of parts &amp; learning, our famous <hi>Monarchs</hi> have ſtill from time to time ſince the <hi>Reformation</hi> beſtowed them, no <hi>Engliſh man</hi> can I am ſure be ignorant. What <hi>Sectaries</hi> give of their own for the maintenance of their Paſtors, in <hi>Gods</hi> name let them have it, &amp; as for the claim of Papiſts to the <hi>Premiſses</hi> we need not fear it, though our Anceſtors of that perſwaſion were the Benefactors; for they that got the <hi>Pope</hi> in <hi>Q Maries</hi> time for the quiet of the Kingdom to conform the <hi>Act of Parliament</hi> that ſold <hi>Abby lands</hi> (which makes our title to them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable upon all accounts whatſoever) will without doubt in conſideration of <hi>Indulgence</hi> do again the like, ſhould any man be ſo ſcrupulous as to deſire their releaſe to that little which is ſtill left the <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No benefit can there be to invent new <hi>Sects,</hi> or to continue them, becauſe <hi>Liberty</hi> to do as they pleaſe will quite cool (as I ſaid the <hi>zeal</hi> of men delighted with novelties, nor ſhall the perſons of many now amongſt us be admired, who under pretence of ſuffering for <hi>God,</hi> devour Widdows &amp; Orphans, &amp; by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees become the ruine both of <hi>Church</hi> &amp; <hi>State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How great &amp; ſtrong therefore muſt the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> grow by this <hi>Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence,</hi> when 'twil be no advantage for Deceivers (that now daily rage) to rob her of her children, &amp; what ſhall hinder the ſheep that went aſtray to return when they find neither pleaſure nor profit in their folly? Nor ſhall we then (to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent wonder of mankind be always <hi>conſulting about Religion,</hi> as our very <hi>Gramer</hi> has it; nor wi l our <hi>Parliaments</hi> be longer troubled with the inſolencies of <hi>Papiſts</hi> &amp; <hi>Phanatiques,</hi> which has been the common artifice to divert ſober motions, when they ran counter to the private intereſt of a few. Having thus ſtated each party's <hi>principles &amp; caſe</hi> as ful as I could (&amp; really believing <hi>Toleration</hi> will ſo ſettle us in our <hi>ſpiritual &amp;</hi> temporal concerns, that in a trice neither of them will have any conſiderable enemies left) now defie our <hi>Diſſenters</hi> themſelves to prevent their own ruine, though I have diſcover'd every thing, &amp; ſhow'd them the very <hi>trap</hi> and <hi>pitfall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All that theit <hi>Leaders</hi> can (I am ſure) do, is (as ſome have already done) to <hi>hinder</hi> underhand that <hi>Indulgence</hi> which they ſeem ſo earneſtly to deſire; for they are ſenſible enough (as I mention'd) that they will hereby not only looſe the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent benefit they make of their <hi>followers</hi> (who in peace will ſoon be weary of them) but alſo that a l heir rebellious deſigns muſt be fruſtrated, as being never able to perſwade them to fight the <hi>battai s</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> or in plain E gliſh to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell,</hi> that already enjoy what they hope for by the danger: &amp; beſides al theſe true reaſons, <hi>Pitty</hi> it ſelf caſt's ſomething into the <hi>Ballanci;</hi> for if <hi>the righteous man be merciful to his beaſt,</hi> much more ought we ſo to be poor well meaning Chriſtians.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>LONDON. <date>1662.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
